I accidentally made this app to improve
my life and it was so effective that it
reduced my screen time by 99%. So far
after making this, I've read multiple
books in a week. I've not missed any gym
sessions and I no longer have to rely on
discipline. The app is called Habits
First. And how it works is that it
forces you to finish your habits in
order to unlock your social media apps
or addictive apps on your phone. It
surprisingly made it super motivating to
actually finish my habits to unlock
addictive apps like YouTube and social
media. So, in this video, I want to
share with you the best features that
make this the ultimate screen time app
and also what I've learned in the
process of making this because I'm tired
of paying for subscription screen time
apps. I'm making this app completely for
free. help. If you do end up trying it,
feel free to email me and I would love
to hop on a call with you guys who try
it out in the first month just to hear
about what's confusing, what's missing,
and what new features you'd want in this
app, which is a good excuse to talk
about the sponsor of this video,
Granola, because calls are exactly what
I use it for. So, as someone who went
from working in a big corporate company
to now being self-employed, one of the
things that has stayed the same is
having to jump on work calls. And
because of that, I've tested many
different workflows to optimize for
that. And among everything that I've
tried, the best solution that I found
for this is a tool called Granola. So
Granola is an app that automatically
take notes from any meeting that you
join. It automatically detects a
meeting, automatically transcribes it,
and automatically creates a summary when
you're done with the call. The reason
why Granola stands out to me so much is
because it literally works with every
single app on your computer. It doesn't
matter if you're doing a call in Discord
or Zoom or Google Meets. It auto detects
a call and helps you take notes. There's
no bot that joins in that gives everyone
pressure and you can still jot down
notes in the app and see it after the
call ends. This single app has reduced
the pressure off so much work calls. I
know that every single detail is being
captured and I can just focus on the
thing that we're discussing instead of
being distracted typing or writing notes
down. When the meeting's done, you get
the transcript, you get the summary, and
you also get your personal notes. If you
use Obsidian like me, it's also super
easy to sync and add to your personal
vault. You can try for free through the
link in the description. The basic plan
is completely free and covers more than
enough for most people with unlimited
transcriptions. But yeah, let's get back
to the video. The first thing you're
probably thinking is why not just rely
on discipline for reducing your screen
time? Like that seems far more reliable
for the habits you actually want to do.
What I found is that discipline works
really well for things like going to the
gym consistently and having a routine,
but it doesn't work that well when it
comes to you and your smartphone. And
the reason for that is because it's not
a battle between you and your phone.
It's a battle between you and millions
of engineers and millions of content
creators creating engaging apps,
engaging content for you to spend more
time on. So, if you don't have tools to
help you limit that usage, it's more
likely than not that you're going to be
sucked down into an endless rabbit hole.
Like recently, I was listening to this
podcast with Sam Elman and he downloaded
Tik Tok to try and see what the users
are posting and try to learn more as
sort of market research. And within a
couple of weeks or maybe even a couple
of days, he was addicted to Tik Tok. and
he said he spent 3 hours just scrolling
Tik Tok reels before he realized that he
had to just delete the app completely.
So no matter how strong your discipline
is, it's almost like a battle of
attrition. Over time, if your discipline
just dips for a single day or single
moment, you might find yourself spending
way too much time than you would want on
your phone. That's the reason why now
there's a big trend towards just
completely quitting social media
entirely or quitting the internet
entirely and using stuff like the iPhone
where you just don't have those apps
installed. But if you're watching this
video, I would probably bet that you
probably don't watch brain rot content.
Like you probably don't watch useless,
mindless entertainment content, whether
that's on Instagram, YouTube, or X. You
probably watch educational videos, stuff
that actually brings value to your life.
And so the issue is not cutting out
social media entirely. It's having a way
to limit or naturally minimize the time
that you use it so you have the maximum
utility from social media apps. So what
is the reason that most screen time apps
fail? In my opinion, the reason why most
screen time apps fail is because you're
rewarding the wrong behavior. Most
screen time apps either have you limit
the maximum amount of time that you can
use in a day or you can set it so that
it's only available to be used at
certain times of the day. But in my
experience in using that and also
recommending people around me to have
something like this set up, what I found
is that over time there's basically no
motivation to keep this up. And most
people either find other distractions or
they end up just removing the block or
deleting the app completely. So at at
least for me, the times that I've been
able to do something really difficult
consistently over long periods of time
is when there was some sort of reward
associated with it. The reward acts like
a forcing function for you to do
something that's uncomfortable. So, I
made a prototype app with this mechanism
and it worked super well, almost too
well. I made it so that I had to either
listen to an audiobook or read for 30
minutes in order to unlock social media
apps for 5 minutes. Then after 5
minutes, it would lock again and it
would take another 30 minutes of reading
or listening to unlock it again. And
just by doing that, I was able to finish
multiple books in a week. And it just
seemed like there was magical time that
I created. In the book, Atomic Habits,
the author talks about this concept for
building positive habit loops. And
basically, the reward is the final step
of the habit loop. And it helps you
satisfy your craving and reinforce the
behavior that you want. After I set this
up on my phone, whenever I would pull
out my phone in the middle of the day,
even if I only had a minute, now usually
that might be just checking something on
social media, I would instead read for a
minute just so that I could add up extra
experience points to unlock social media
later in the day. Personally, I have not
seen any screen time apps build in this
mechanism, but I think this mechanism
actually hijacks the addictive nature of
social media apps and uses it in your
favor. Because the more addicting the
social media app is, the more motivated
you're going to be to finish any
particular habit. Like it could be
hitting 10,000 steps or it could be
learning or using an for a certain
amount of time in a day. At least that's
my personal experience and it's actually
become motivating for me to open up the
books app instead of opening up x.com.
Let me just show you what the app looks
like and you guys can let me know what
you think and I can also improve this
app and make this a cool project for us
to use. So, my first big issue with most
screen time apps that I've used in the
past is that it's too hard to set up.
There are some screen time apps that
require you to fill out a survey, an
extended survey before they just show
you a payw wall. And that just leads me
to uninstalling the app. And there's
some other ones that require you to even
like purchase something, get something
shipped to your house before you can
block apps. But I want to make something
that was as simple as possible so you
can get set up as quickly as possible
with no payw wall. So, I want there to
be as few clicks as possible. So, how it
works is when you download the app and
you open it, it explains what the app
does. It gets your permission for screen
time, Apple Health, and other
permissions for ways to block apps. And
then you can just create your first
block. You don't have to create an
account. You don't have to sign up for
any free trial. You can just use it to
improve your life immediately. So, in
order to make the app easy to use, I
also wanted there to be as few layouts
as possible. Like there are certain apps
I've used for reducing my screen time
that was really complex to even find how
to change things or find how it works at
all. So this one just has three pages.
There are all your blocks. There's your
insights that tells you how much screen
time that you've used. And then there's
your settings. And the second issue I
wanted to solve with most screen time
apps was subscription fees. A wise man
once said that you should be the change
you want to see in the world. So this
app is not going to have a subscription
fee. Not now or anytime in the future. I
also think in general that apps with
subscription fees are slowly dying
because of how fast AI is growing and
progressing and there's this massive
resurgence of open source apps. So I
think people are just naturally drifting
towards options where they don't have to
pay a monthly subscription. The way that
I think about this is if this app ends
up getting a lot of traction, I will
fund it with this YouTube channel and
avoid having subscription fees. And if
it doesn't get any traction, then I'm
just going to continue using it for
myself and adding features as I need
them. So, sort of a win-win situation.
The third issue with most screen time
apps that I want to solve is that most
screen time apps are too easy to bypass.
If you have used screen time apps, it's
likely that at some point you might have
even accidentally found out a way to
bypass it. And if you can bypass it, it
kind of defeats the entire purpose of
having it in the first place. For those
of you that want to go hardcore, and
that includes myself, I add added some
options where you can make it impossible
to bypass. So the first line of defense
is that you can lock making changes
after you set up a block. The second is
that you can lock deleting the app. And
the third line of defense is if you
actually want to make it impossible, you
can have a friend lock your screen time
password in settings. And if you're on
iOS 27, you literally will not be able
to unlock it unless you have them input
the password. Those are the three main
things that I wanted to improve in terms
of making an ultimate screen time app.
But if you guys have other ideas, let me
know in the comments below. So right now
in terms of integrations, I have Apple
Health which integrates with your phone
for steps or your Apple Watch for your
workout history and you can make it so
that you have to work out before your
social media apps unlock. I also have
locations. So you can block or unblock
apps only at certain locations. I have
this one called beacons which is that
you can block certain rooms in your
house by selecting a Bluetooth device in
that room. So, it it will only unlock or
lock in certain locations in your house.
But yeah, if you guys have other
integrations, definitely let me know.
I'm going to try to add them to this app
so that it can just be the most useful
screen time app that everyone can use.
One of my goals with starting the
channel was always not to just showcase
different tech and tools to help you
optimize your life, but to also make
tools that help you optimize your life.
And if you've been following my channel
for a while, then you know that two
years ago, I spent an entire year and
more uh trying to build this one app
full-time. And that idea didn't really
work. We weren't able to reach product
market fit. But I learned a ton from
that experience. And with the tools that
we have now, I want to try again. But
this time, the first thing I'm doing is
releasing it, getting feedback, and
iterating on it. And I think screen time
is something that's extremely growingly
more important in this day and age,
especially with more and more uh
addictive apps and more and more AI
content. So, I think it makes sense to
build new tools with new mechanisms that
help you counteract that. And yeah,
that's it for this video. I'll see you
next video. Comment below. I'll try to
respond to all the comments. And I'll
see you next one. Let's get it.